Sorry!
すまん！
I missed the vital spot! I'll put you at ease--
急所を外しちまった！すぐ楽に…
Askeladd...
アシェ…ラッド…
I wanted to be friends with you...
アンタと…！友達にっ…！
Yeah. Bjorn...
ああ…ビョルン…
You...
お前は…
You are my only...
オレのたったひとりの…
friend.
友達だ
Send me off...
送って…くれ…
Well, then, sorry to keep you waiting, kid.
さて…待たせたな小僧
Come.
来い
I'll play with you.
遊んでやる
LONE WOLF
Damn.
クソ…
He's acting different than usual.
いつもとは違うな…
So? Who do you think is going to win, prince?
で？どっちが勝つと思うね王子？
Want to make a bet?
賭けるかい？
I don't care who wins.
どちらでもかまわぬ。
I'll stop the duel before someone dies.
どちらも死なぬうちに止める
You're no fun!
つまんねェこと言うなよ。
You don't get to see duels
between such skilled warriors every day.
こんな手練れ同士の決闘、そうそう拝めるものじゃねンだぜ？
Well, then, which one do you think is stronger?
では…そなたはどちらが強いと考える
Me? Well...
オレ？ん～そうね…
I guess Askeladd. I bet one pound of silver on him.
アシェラッドかな。ヤツに銀1ポンド！
I'm not going to make a bet.
Why do you think so?
賭けぬぞ。なぜそう思う
Just a feeling. It's his aura.
なんとなく？フンイキ？
Thorfinn defeated you.
トルフィンはそなたに勝ったのであろう。
Is Askeladd even better than that?
アシェラッドはそれ以上か？
You. Prince. Who do you think I am?
てめェ王子…ナメてんな？
There's no way that I'm the weakest one
out of us three. Right?
3人の中でこのオレ様が一番弱ェとか。ありえねェだろうが。あァ？
It's not that simple to tell who's stronger
and who's weaker.
強ェの弱ェのってなァ、そんな単純なもんじゃねェのよ。
Sometimes you win, and sometimes you lose.
It's not easy to rank people. That's the fun part.
勝ったり負けたり、簡単に順序がつかねェのが面白ェんだよ
I'm not interested.
興味ない
You must be a woman.
てめェやっぱ女だろ？
What's wrong, Thorfinn? Come.
どうしたトルフィン？来いよ
I want to finish this before the snow gets worse.
降りが強くなる前に終わらせてェ
I have no choice.
しょうがねぇなァ
Look. Now, it's easier to attack me, right?
ホレ！攻めやすくなったろ？
Come, boy.
来い…坊主
Right?
な？
You still don't understand why it turns out like this?
まだわかんねェのか？なんでこうなるのか
I take back what I said just now.
This isn't a duel.
さっきの訂正。勝負になってねェやこりゃ
Askeladd knows Thorfinn's habits.
He can see through his cover.
トルフィンの奴、クセから何からアシェラッドに見抜かれてら。
These two must have dueled many times.
What's the reason for the duel?
この2人相当やってんな。決闘の理由は？
I don't know. No one told me.
知らぬ。聞いていない
Unbelievable.
ったく…
You never learn, kid.
成長のねェガキだ。
Did you get full of yourself after you beat Thorkell?
トルケルに勝って調子に乗ったか
I'm sick of you.
いいかげんうんざりするぜ…
Stop! That's enough!
やめよ！そこまでだ！
Did you think you could beat me
with only one arm?
片手でこのオレに勝てると思ったか
Come on.
まったく…
Today, I'm feeling damn good.
今日はクソ気分のいい日だぜ
Stop!
やめろ！
Stop. He's passed out.
もうよせ！気絶している！
You win.
そなたの勝ちだ！
You're really going to stop them?
あーあ。ホントに止めやがんの
Thorfinn! Hey! Thorfinn!
トルフィン！おい！トルフィン！
Do you understand? The duel is over.
わかるか？決闘はもう終わったぞ。
You lost.
そなたの負けだ
Enough. It's over now.
よせ。もう終わりだ
You bastard!
てめえェ…！
You passed out.
気を失ったのだ。
He already delivered the deathblow.
すでにとどめを刺されている。
Start over again once your right arm has healed.
右腕が治ってから、またやり直せ
It will end the same way
even after your arm heals.
治っても同じですよ。
It's not because of your wound.
ケガのせいじゃねェ
You're an idiot who loses because he's an idiot.
そのバカはバカだから負ける。
Normally, you know how to think while you fight.
ふだんはちったァ考えて戦うようになってきちゃいるが…
But once you lose your temper,
it all goes to waste.
いっぺん頭に血が上ったら全部台なしだ。
I can tell from where you're looking
that you're going after my neck.
首筋を狙ってるのが目線で丸わかりなんだよ
Losing your temper, shouting loudly,
すぐにブチ切れて…でけェ声だして。
and waving your sword around
is how an idiot fights.
得物振り回すのァバカの戦だ。
Unbelievable. Everyone's the same.
まったくどいつもこいつも…
There's no beauty in it.
美しさのかけらもありゃしねェ
Bjorn is right.
ビョルンの言うとおりさ
I hate warriors.
オレァ戦士ってのが大嫌いだ。
Especially Norse warriors, Vikings.
ノルド戦士…ヴァイキングは特にな
The first man I ever killed was also a Norse warrior.
初めて殺した相手もノルド戦士だった。
He was not a beautiful man.
美しくない男だったぜ
He was my father.
オレの親父だ
Kid...
小僧…
I'm going to tell you something for future reference.
後学のために教えてやろう
I'm going to tell you how to kill someone you hate.
憎い相手の殺し方をな
All right!
よいしょー！
-I'm getting old.
-Watch out behind you.
ガタきてんなァ
後ろ気ぃつけェ
My mother was a slave.
オレは…奴隷の母親から産まれた。
My mother was sick and couldn't work.
お袋は病気で働くことができなかった
So, ever since I was old enough to remember,
なんで物心つく頃にゃ、
I was working in the blacksmith's shop and the stable.
鍛冶場や厩の下働きだった
My body was always covered in
体はいつも灰や煤や
ash, coal, or horse manure,
and was always white or black.
馬のクソやらで白かったり黒かったりでな。
They gave me the nickname "Askeladd."
ついたアダ名が“アシェラッド”
It means "covered in ash."
“灰まみれ”って意味だ
Olaf has returned!
ウォラフ様が帰っていらしたぞー！
He was victorious again!
また大勝利だとよぉ！
My father was from a powerful family in Jutland.
親父はユトランドの豪族だった
-Olaf!
-Welcome back, Olaf!
ウォラフ様ー！！
おかえりなさいウォラフ様！
He loved booze, women and killing people.
酒と女と殺しが好きな…まァ、
He was a Viking,
just like those you'd find anywhere else.
どこにでもいるようなヴァイキングだ
I heard he had lots of kids like me
with random women here and there.
オレみたいなガキを、あちこちの女に産ませてたらしいが
But he only named the older kids
he had with his legal wife.
名を与えたのは本妻の産んだ、年長の子供たちだけだった
He probably didn't even know
what his other kids looked like.
それ以外のガキなんざ…顔も覚えちゃいなかっただろうぜ
I heard that my mother
お袋は若い頃、
was one of my father's favorite slaves
when she was younger.
親父のお気に入りの奴隷だったそうだが
But after she fell ill, he treated her like a dog.
病を得てからは、犬と同じ扱いだった
For me, life had always been hard.
生きることがつらいのはオレにとっちゃ当たり前のことだったが
But it was different for my mother.
どうやら、お袋は違ったようだ
My mother often told me about
the hero Artorius, one of our ancestors.
お袋はよく、先祖の英雄アルトリウスの話をした。
She told the same story many times.
同じ話を何度もした。
The legend was about a general
who protected my mother's homeland
500年前、蛮族の侵入から
from being invaded by savages 500 years ago.
お袋の故郷を守った将軍の伝説だ。
My mother believed the legend's prophecy
that the hero would be resurrected.
お袋は英雄復活の伝説を信じていた
She believed that he would return
to free her from illness and enslavement.
自分を病や奴隷身分から解き放ってくれる者の再来をな…
She kept repeating it.
あんまり繰り返すもんだからよ。
So, I started to believe it, too.
オレも信じるようになった
She said that far to the west,
はるか西の彼方…
in a land across the sea
where ordinary people cannot reach,
常人にはたどりつくことのできない彼岸の地に、
there lies a paradise where the hero Artorius lives.
英雄アルトリウスの住む楽土があるという
A paradise, where peace,
prosperity and eternal life is promised.
平和と豊穣、不老不死が約束された理想郷だ
The hero is still there now, healing his battle wounds.
英雄はそこで、今も戦の傷を癒やしているらしい。
Someday, he will come
leading an army to slay the savages
いつの日か彼は万軍を従え来て、蛮族どもを誅し、
and conquer the world.
この世を平定して下さる。
My mother's family kept waiting for him.
お袋の一族は…それを待ち続けた。
They waited for 500 years.
待ちに待って500年。
The hero hasn't appeared yet.
英雄はまだ現れない
But just think about it.
だが考えてもみろよ。
If our ancestor really was living in such a nice place,
もし本当にご先祖様がそんないい所に暮らしてるならよ。
he'd never choose to come back to a world like this.
すき好んでこんな世界に帰ってくるわきゃアねェ
When I was 11, my mother's heart finally snapped.
そして…オレが11の時ついにお袋の心が折れた
Mother!
母さん！
Of all the things that could happen,
she thought that my father, who was just passing by,
よりにもよって…たまたま通りかかった親父のことを、
was the hero Artorius.
英雄アルトリウスと勘違いしたらしい
I realized in an instant.
一瞬で悟った。
If Artorius wasn't going to
come save my mother in that moment,
今この時アルトリウスがお袋を助けに来ないのなら、
then he's never going to come.
そんな者は永遠に来ないのだと
Do you understand, kids?
わかるか若造ども。
Someone must do it.
誰かがやらねばならん。
A person, not a hero, and not a god.
英雄でも神でもねェ。誰かがな
It's weird.
不思議なもんだ
I had never used a sword before
but it felt right in my hands.
初めて使ったのに、剣はオレの手によくなじんだ
I knew how to swing it.
どう振ればいいのか、わかっていた
I thought of it as proof that I had the blood of
that damn bastard flowing through my veins.
オレの体に目の前のクソ野郎の血が流れている証拠だと思った
I'm so ashamed.
情けねェ話さ。
It makes me want to cry.
涙が出るぜ
You.
お前…
Are you her child?
その女の子か
Are you my child?
ワシの子か？
Yes.
そうです
You have potential.
見込みがある。
You live in the hall starting today.
今日から館に住め
I knew he wasn't someone who an 11-year-old could kill.
さすがに11歳のガキに殺れる相手とは思ってなかった。
But I succeeded in getting my father to notice me.
まずは親父の目にとまること。成功だ
I behaved myself in the hall.
館では行儀よくしていたよ。
I didn't slack off in my training
for the military arts or horsemanship.
武術や馬術の鍛錬を怠らなかった。
I even got along well with my half-brothers.
腹違いの兄貴たちとも、うまくやってた
Good job, Askeladd.
I always made sure I showed respect to my father.
いつも親父を立てるように気を遣ってな
I was a loyal son and didn't forget
that he saved me from my life as a slave.
奴隷暮らしから救ってくれた恩を決して忘れない忠実な息子だった
Before long, everyone
started to accept me as my father's son.
じきに周りも身内も、
すっかりオレを親父の子として受け入れるようになった
I worked on it for two years.
この作業に2年をかけたぜ
I was after two things.
狙いは2つ
I wanted to catch him with his guard down,
and I wanted the right to inherit his property.
親父の油断と、遺産の相続権だ
I wish you could have seen it.
お前らにも見せてやりたかったよ。
His face had this look, like he was asking, "Why?"
親父のあの“何故！？”ってツラ…！
I used my brother's sword.
使ったのは兄貴の剣だ。
I chose someone who didn't
get along with my father and stole his sword.
親父と仲の悪い奴から選んで盗んだ
My other brothers thought
he was the one who did it and hanged him.
他の兄貴たちは犯人と思い込んで、そいつをリンチにかけちまいやんの。
They're so simple-minded.
全く単純な奴らだぜ
They're stupid and filthy.
バカで不潔で…
The have nothing except for their own greed.
テメェの欲望以外に何もねェクソどもさ。
People without beauty like them
started popping up everywhere
ああいう美しくねェ奴らが、そこら中からわいて出てきて
and throwing their weight around.
幅を利かせやがる。
There's no end to it, no matter how many I kill.
いくらブチ殺してもキリがねェ
I don't care whether it's Artorius, Ragnarok,
or the Last Judgment.
アルトリウスでもラグナロクでも、最後の審判でも何でもいいからよ。
If you're really going to come,
then you'd better hurry.
マジに来るなら、急いでもらいたいもんだぜ
Well, when that happens, I bet they're not going to
let me keep on living either though.
ま。そん時ゃオレも…生きちゃいられねェだろうがな
Well, that was a long story. Anyway, Thorfinn...
ああ長くなったな。要するにだトルフィン
you still can't even kill me
even though it's been 10 years.
10年以上かけてオレひとり倒せないお前は…
That means you're an idiot.
ボンクラだって話さ
Shut up!
うるせぇ！
I'm...
オレは！
I'm going to kill you, no matter what happens!
オレは何があってもテメェを殺す！
I'm going to kill you, no matter what!
ぜってぇ殺してやる！
Come on.
ったく…
You're still saying that? Right after what I told you?
言ってるそばからそれかよ
You're just like a dog chasing after food.
犬みてェに餌につられて駆け回りやがって…
I really am thankful for all your hard work.
おめぇの働きにゃあマジで頭が下がるよ。
All I have to do is put on an act
having these duels with you.
茶番みてェな決闘につきあってやるだけで、
And then you'd go run off
and even fight someone like Thorkell.
あのトルケルにまでホイホイ挑んでいくんだもんなぁ
You're a useful kid.
便利なガキだよ。お前は
Unbelievable.
まったく…
I must thank Thors, too.
トールズにも感謝しねェとな
Wait.
待て…
Wait!
待て…！
Stop.
もうよせ
Shut up! Shut up! Shut up! Be quiet!
うるせぇ！うるせぇ！うるせえぇっ！！黙れえぇっ！
Now is the time to heal your wounds.
今は傷を癒やせ
I said wait.
ちやがれ…
Won't you stop?
よさぬか！
How pathetic.
はぁーあ！なっさけね…
Oh, dear. You're stiff now, Bjorn.
やれやれ。すっかり固くなっちまったなビョルン
Why me?
何故…私なのだ。
You're the hero's descendant, Askeladd.
英雄の末裔はそなたであろう。アシェラッド。
And you're quick-witted.
才気もある。
Don't you want to become the king yourself
and change the world?
己自身が王となり、世を変えようとは思わぬのか？
You're joking, right?
ご冗談でしょ。
Weren't you listening just now?
話聞いてなかったんですか？
You're more suited to be the king.
あなたのほうが王にふさわしい。
More than me or King Sweyn.
オレやスヴェン王よりもね
I can tell by looking at your face.
顔見りゃわかります
I'm just a Viking.
オレァただのヴァイキングですよ